A Guide to the Borden Family Papers, 1845-1999
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Borden Family Papers, 1845-1999
Library of Virginia
37960
2.4 cubic feet (6 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. James M. Baylor, 28 February 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mary Fitzgerald Borden, daughter of Edmond Boxley (1854-1936) and Virginia Lewis Crews Borden (1861-1942), was born 22 December 1889 in Gretna (Pittsylvania County), Virginia. James Paul Borden, son of Benjamin Franklin (1849-1920) and Sallie Catherine Pitman Borden (1848-1923), was born 3 December 1892 in Harrisville (Shenandoah County), Virginia. Mary and James Borden married 12 December 1917 at the Fitzgerald estate, "Sunnyside", in Pittsylvania County, Virginia. They lived in Front Royal, Virginia, where James worked for the Royal Telephone Company. In 1932 they moved to Charlottesville, Virginia, where James worked for Virginia Telephone and Telegraph Company. They had three children, Virginia Crews, James P. Jr., and Benjamin Franklin, III.
Scope and Content Information
Genealogical research files, 1845-1999 (bulk 1955-1977), of James and Mary Fitzgerald Borden on the Borden, Fitzgerald, and related families of Accomac, Campbell, Henrico, Orange, Pittsylvania, and Shenandoah Counties, Virginia; and Ohio. Includes bible records, clippings, correspondence, diaries, obituaries, genealogical charts, maps, photographs, transcripts of wills and bibles, and abstracts from court records.
Organization
Organized into the following series and subseries: I. James P. Borden Files, 1845-1999 - Subseries 1. Genealogy of the Borden families in Shenandoah County, Virginia (1958), Subseries 2. Family Research Files, 1845-1999; II. Mary Fitzgerald Borden Files, 1947-1991 - Subseries 1. Climbing the Family Tree, Subseries 2. Family Research Files, 1947-1991.
Contents List
- James P. Borden files (Box 1-5)
  This series contains genealogical research gathered by James Borden on the Borden and related Goodman, Hockman, Phillips, Pitman, Ramey, and Windle families of Shenandoah County, Virginia; and Ohio. Includes chapters from his book, Genealogy of the Borden families in Shenandoah County, Virginia, and family research files. Contains bibles, correspondence, diaries, newspaper clippings, photographs, epitaphs, and transcripts of wills and court records.
  - Genealogy of the Borden families in Shenandoah County, Virginia (Box-folder Box 1 - Box 2, Folder 16)
    This subseries contains an incomplete copy of James Borden's book, Genealogy of the Borden families in Shenandoah County, Virginia, compiled in 1958. An original copy of the entire book is not present in the collection, but included are some of the completed chapters, along with the title page, preface, and table of contents. The book traces the ancestry of James Borden's family beginning with Runald and Catharine Borden of Shenandoah County, Virginia. Includes information James gathered from court records, bibles, wills, obituaries, newspaper clippings, graveyards, and other family members. Each section is numbered and labeled.
    - Table of contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Title page (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Preface (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Preface (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Borden name (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Borden, Runald and Catharine (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Borden, George and Sophia Hawn (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Borden, William and Rebecca Snarr (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Section 1, Page 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Section 1, Page 2 (Phillips family) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Section 1, Page 3 (Phillips family) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Section 1, Page 4 (Phillips family) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Section 1, Page 5 (Borden, Ollie) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Section 1, Page 6 (Borden, Ollie) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Section 1, Page 6A (Borden, Joel L.) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Section 1, Page 7 (Borden, Christian David) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Section 1, Page 8 (Borden, Gilbert L.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Section 1, Page 9 (Borden, Gilbert L.) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Section 1, Page 10 (Borden, Floyd D.) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Section 2, Page 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Section 2, Page 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Section 3, Page 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Section 3, Page 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Section 3, Page 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Section 4, Page 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Section 4, Page 2 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Section 4, Page 3 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Section 5, Page 7 (Hoekman and Ramey) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Section 5, Page 8 (Ramey family) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Section 5, Page 15 (Borden, Harry L.) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Section 5, Page 17 (Borden, Harry L.) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Section 5, Page 18 (Borden, Harry L.) (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Section 5, Page 18A (Borden, Harry L, and Mary E.) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Section 5, Page 19 (Borden, Mattie and Otto W.) (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Section 5, Page 20 (Borden, Otto W.) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Section 5, Page 21 (Raymond Jones family) (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Section 5, Page 22 (Borden, Otto W.) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Section 5, Page 23 (Borden, Otto W.- obituary) (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Section 5, Page 24 (Borden, Jesse D.) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Section 5, Page 24A (Borden, Wilson) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Section 5, Page 25 (Borden, Jesse D.) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Section 5, Page 26 (Borden, Jesse D.) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Section 5, Page 26A (Borden, Sallie Haskins Wilson) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Section 5, Page 27 (Borden, James P., Sr.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Section 5, Page 27A (Borden, James P., Sr. - Baylor, James M.) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Section 5, Page 29 (Borden, James P., Sr., and Mary Fitzgerald) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Section 5, Page 30 (Borden, James P., Sr., - marriage announcement) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Section 5, Page 31 (Borden, James P., Sr., - Borden, Crews) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Section 5, Page 31A (Borden, James P., Sr., Borden, Crews) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Section 5, Page 32 (Borden, James P., Sr.- Borden, James P., Jr.) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Section 5, Page 35 (Borden, James P., Sr., - Borden, Benjamin F., III) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Section 6, Page 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Section 6, Page 2 (Borden, Taylor - Borden, Bernie) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Section 6, Page 3 (Borden, Bernie) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Section 6, Page 3A (Borden, Phillip) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Section 6, Page 3B (Borden, Phillip) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Section 6, Page 4 (Borden, Albert) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Section 7, Page 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Family research files (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17 - Box 5)
    This subseries contains family research files which include correspondence, pedigree charts, photographs, information from published sources, source material received from other individuals, and transcripts of wills and bibles. Some of the materials may have been included in Borden's book, but were not clearly marked as so. Of note are the family group sheets, and the attendance records, correspondence, flyers, and photographs from annual reunions held by the Borden family, 1924-1977. Also included is a copy of Levi Pitman's diary, 1847-1892, of Mt. Olive (Shenandoah County), Virginia, containing descriptions of daily life and the construction of the Mt. Hebron Church in Shenandoah County, Virginia. A history of St. John's United Church of Christ in Toms Brook, Shenandoah County, Virginia is also included in the collection, along with information on the Borden family lines in New York and England.
    - Borden, Albert L. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Borden, Benjamin (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Borden, Benjamin F., Family reunions, 1924-1957 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Borden, Benjamin F., Family reunions, 1958-1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Borden, Benjamin F., Family reunions, Photographs, c. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Borden, Benjamin F., Misc., 1848-1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Borden, Benjamin F., Misc. family photographs, c. 1900 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Borden, Frederick, c. 1900-1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Borden, James E. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Borden, James P., Family correspondence, 1955-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Borden, James P., Family correspondence, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Borden, James P., Personal notes and pictures, 1910-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Borden, Rebecca Snarr (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Borden, Reynard, Part 1, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Borden, Reynard, Part 2, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Borden, Robert C., 1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Borden family replies (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Borden family, English line, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Borden family, New York line (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Borden family, New York line, Borden, James E. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Borden family, New York line, Borden, Rebecca (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Borden family, New York line, Borden, Richard (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Borden family, New York line, Borden, Richard (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Clement, Rebecca Borden (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hayden, Cinda Ramey, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pearce, Louice Borden, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Pitman, Emanuel (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Pitman, Emanuel, Will (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Pitman, Esther Kathryn, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Pitman, Esther Miriam (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Pitman, Frank, 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Pitman, Henry (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Pitman, J. Emanuel, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Pitman, Jacob (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Pitman, Levi (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Pitman, Levi, Bible (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary, 1845-1892 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary Part 1, 1845-1850 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary Part 2, 1850-1853 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary Part 3, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary Part 4, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary Part 5, 1854-1870 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary, Church sayings, 1846-1847 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary, Church sayings, 1847 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary, Church sayings, 1847 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary, Church sayings, 1847 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Pitman, Levi, Diary, Misc. (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Pitman, Martin (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Pitman, Victoria (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Pitman family, 1937-1973 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Pitman family, Walthers, Emily, 1966-1977 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Windle, Augustine (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Windle, Jacob (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Windle family, Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Windle and Pitman families, Miscellaneous, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - St. John's United Church (Toms Brook, Va.), 1951-1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Shenandoah County (Va.), Maps (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Stirewalt, W.J., 1957-1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Talk to North Carolina Colonial Dames, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Blank forms (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, c. 1910-1958 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1923-1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Mary Fitzgerald Borden files (Box 6)
  This series contains genealogical research gathered by Mary Fitzgerald Borden on the Fitzgerald and related Crews and Graves families of Accomac, Campbell, Henrico, Orange, and Pittsylvania Counties, Virginia. Includes chapters from her book, Climbing the Family Tree, and family research files. Contains correspondence, family group sheets, obituaries, and newspaper clippings.
  - Climbing the Family Tree (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1-14)
    This subseries contains an incomplete copy of Mary Fitzgerald Borden's book, Climbing the Family Tree, compiled in 1963. An original copy of the entire book is not present in the collection, but included are some of the completed chapters, along with the title page, preface, and table of contents. The book traces the ancestry of Mary Fitzgerald Borden, beginning with James Crews of Henrico County, Virginia, and Edmund Fitzgerald of Ireland. Each section is numbered and labeled.
    - Preface (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 2 and 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Chapters 4 and 5 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Chapters 6 and 7 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Chapters 8 and 9 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 10 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Chapter 12 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Chapters 13 and 14 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Chapter 16 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Chapter 17 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Chapter 18 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 19 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Chapters 22 and 23 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Chapters 24, 25 and 26 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Family research files (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 15-20)
    This subseries contains correspondence, an article entitled "Dedicating a Home," by Mary Fitzgerald Borden, pedigree charts, obituaries, and miscellaneous newspaper announcements. Also included are Mary Fitzgerald Borden's wishes for her funeral arrangements, burial, and division of estate.
    - Extra sheets for book (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Borden, Mary Fitzgerald, 1963-1976 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Fitzgerald, Edmond Boxley, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Fitzgerald, Ned, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Fitzgerald, Susan M., 1991 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous announcements, 1947-1950 (Box 6, Folder 20)